Guide to the William Pickens Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Pickens papers
1875-1991
1910-1954
JWJ MSS 125
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.29
(6 boxes)
Pickens, William, 1881-1954
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1899-1991. II. Scrapbooks, Ephemera, and Realia, 1875-1991.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Manuscript and printed works, scrapbooks, ephemera, and realia documenting the career of William Pickens. Writings of Pickens and others on African-American culture, emancipation and civil rights are present, as are scrapbooks, ephemera, and commemorative items documenting Pickens' academic accomplishments, including with Phi Beta Kappa, career as a civil servant in the United States Savings Bonds Program of the Treasury Department, and civil rights activist. Photographs of Pickens' Yale College class and of Pickens at a 1948 reception for W. E. B. Du Bois are also present.
William Pickens
William Pickens (1881-1954, Yale 1904), American educator, essayist, and orator. Pickens was admitted to Phi Beta Kappa upon graduation from Yale and then received a master's degree from Fisk University in 1908 and a Doctor of Letters from Selma University in 1915. Pickens was a field secretary for the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, and he wrote extensively on racial issues.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Pickens III, 2001
African Americans -- Civil rights; Racism -- United States; African American civil rights workers; Civil rights workers -- United States; United States -- Race relations; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; African American civil rights workers -- United States -- 20th Century; Civil rights workers -- United States -- 20th Century; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People; Pickens, William, 1881-1954; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
- Writings, 1899-1991; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Writings by Pickens and Writings by Others.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains manuscript and printed works by William Pickens and others.
  - Writings by Pickens
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Abraham Lincoln, Man and Statesman printed pamphlets, 1910, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Frederick Douglass and the Spirit of Freedom printed pamphlet, 1931-1931
    - Fifty Years of Emancipation printed pamphlet
    - The Kind of Democracy the Negro Race Expects printed pamphet, 1918-1918
    - The Lowest Struggler in the Struggle for Democracy printed pamphlet, 1918-1918
    - The Negro in the Great War printed pamphlet, 1918-1918
    - The Problem of Our Public School printed pamphlet, 1914-1914
  - Writings by Others
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Barber, J. Max, How They Became Distinguished printed pamphlet, circa 1920
    - Davis, John P., The Negro and TVA: Reply to the NAACP, 1935-1935
    - Motteau, A., Esperanto-English Dictionary, signed by Pickens, 1906-1906
    - Phi Beta Kappa Associates booklet, with Yale Club newsletter featuring Pickens, 1991-1991
    - Razaf, Andy and J. Rosamond Johnson, That's Why I Buy Bonds sheet music, inscribed from Razaf to Pickens, with material pertaining to a luncheon in Pickens' honor and a 1942 copy of a speech given by Pickens on communism, 1950-1950
    - Trico Public Forum proceedings, 1936-1936
    - Yale College, Memories of 1904 at Yale booklet, signed by Pickens, 1913-1913
- Scrapbooks, Ephemera, and Realia, 1875-1991; Series II; 2.59; (5 boxes) + 1 broadside, 1 art
  Series II includes materials commemorating the life and career of William Pickens. Scrapbooks document his civic achievements, and ephemera from Yale College, Phi Beta Kappa, and other academic and cultural organizations and events document Pickens' academic and activist career.
  Series II is arranged in no particular order.
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1902-1950; 3 (Box 2)
  - Letter book given to Pickens upon his retirement from government service, 1950-1950
  - Guest book from the ceremony of the donation of a portrait of Pickens to the Yale Club, 1991 April 22 (Box 3)
  - Graduation cap from Yale, 1904-1904
  - Phi Beta Kappa key, 1904-1904
  - Reproduction of the Liberty Bell awarded to Pickens for his participation in the Patriotic Service U. S. Savings Bond Program upon his retirement, 1950-1950 (Box 4)
  - Coins and buttons, 1875-1944
    For detailed description of the coins and buttons, see the gift inventory in the first box of the collection.
  - Yale College diploma roll container, 1904-1904 (Box 5)
  - Yale College diploma, 1904-1904 (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - Yale College class photographs, 1949-1950
  - Phi Beta Kappa admission certificate, 1945-1945
  - Esperanto language certificate, 1906-1906
  - Photograph taken at a reception for W. E. B. DuBois, 1948-1948
  - Little Rock, Arkansas public high school diploma, 1899-1899
- Printed works, 1940-1955 (Box A)
  Includes mid-20th century editions of the American Blue Book, a Yale College class book, Who's Who in America, Who's Who in the East, a Phi Beta Kappa Directory, and an Alumni Directory of Yale University.
- Printed works, 1940-1955 (Box B)
  Contains mid-20th century editions of Who's Who in America and a 250th anniversary Yale publication.